do you have any
direct uh method
to overcome this sense of
ownership uh contemplate through your
ownership that which you
own so take up that which you you regard
as yours and then
see how or rather where it is rooted at
whether in your sense of control or
weaing something else that it isn't
yours so for example the body take up
the body my
body is that sense of my body is that
the center of it or would this body be
depending upon all these individual
organs within that sense of ownership of
this body that uh that are required to be
body that uh that are required to be
operating that I cannot
control if those organs were to fail
would I be able to entertain the notion
of this body is mine if this body dies
right right in front of me
so you realize you couldn't So you
you're you're perverting the order by
regarding by giving the priority of that
sense of self of my master of this body
uh and then when you think about the
individual organs you don't think about
them within that sense of Mastery you
think about left right before or after
that's why you don't approach it so the
closest to a method would be to
contemplate Within
this ownership so you can't leave the
ownership so you can't leave the
ownership out and contemplate things
rightly because the whole point of
contemplation is to experience the non
ownership and you experience the non
ownership when you see that this body no
matter how much it's in your control
it's heart is rooted in that which you
cannot even conceive controlling such as
heart breathing lungs pumping blood uh
operating organs functioning brain you
have you can't even conceive how it
would be to control those things or have
say in they're operating yet they are
the fundamental basis for the notion of your
fundamental basis for the notion of your
body as a whole that you do own
mistakenly CU we think we come we myself
comes first yes yeah people I come first thus
first yes yeah people I come first thus
this is for me this is mine it's other
way around it's because I take all this
to be mine I develop a sense of I
am but that sense of I am can be undone
not by denying you know by saying
there's no self there's not really me
look everything is changing this is not
no you need to take up that sense of I
am and then see that it's founded upon
things that cannot be yours then
automatically your experience is the
experience of not I am reversing them St
yeah draining basically draining them
they the kind of the structure stays the
same but what has drained away is that
appropriation from
it that's why the Buddha would say for
an Aran is like a palm stump cut at its
root so the stamp the branches that
grown they stayed but now they're then
done they're petrified they're still
there as the way person's experience
might have proliferated throughout the
ignorant life but once you approve that
ignorance once you remove that
appropriation it stops proliferating and
then just stays like a palm stump until
even that breaks apart in par
in so if
you lose that or get rid of that sense
of ownership
your personality doesn't how does your
personality well anything in your
personality that was depending upon the
ownership that will disappear but there
are other things that were not depending
upon ownership they were depending upon
like Hollow habits habits that were not
rooted in greed diversion delusion that
stays that's why as I said many times
and in the sutas you read often people
cannot tell in arant
externally and even another arand cannot
come and see the I don't know some
special AA around oh he's no they can
tell in Aran when they start discussing
each other's understanding of dhama and
they can see oh yeah he understood this
probably to the extent of course then
the Buddha or somebody like with with
very very developed mind could see
little traits little things and based on
which he could tell the other person's
mind but on an average you can't even
like Sara couldn't tell in some cases
that the person was an Arun then he
would go to the Buddha and said where
was his rebirth he saids what do you
mean didn't he say he was an AR yeah he
did but he was associating with some not
some reputable families and so on he
said well that's that's not why person
is blame worthy person is blame worthy
because uh they leave this body they
take another body as in they keep remain
bound with Sam Sada uh but I can tell
you he wasn't he wasn't blame he was an
arant even before he died but s couldn't
see it so the or the other that that that
it so the or the other that that that
famous one was like really harsh in his
speech and the people were often
offended and then the Buddha said oh
it's his old habits that they were not
rooted in ill will or or greed or
anything like that but obviously you
would come across as very angry Furious
of course that doesn't mean like oh okay
so I don't have to you will know that
you will know which habits can stay once
you're in Aran or on the way of becoming
one you can't decide that beforehand oh
these are my uh neutral habits so you
have to take them all with caution if
you're in a state of PJ you can't trust
any of your habits so you have to keep
investigating any of it if it's rooted
on Greed div version delusion and truly
truly when you dismantle everything that
shouldn't be there whatever's left then
you know that can be left so this is
very different from uh saying that the
self doesn't exist there is there is no
self yeah the Buddha never said that
when he asked him does the self exist he
wouldn't say it does the self does not
exist he wouldn't answer it no it's a
it's a shortcut it's a quick fix in
terms of expl satisfying explanation but
it's not a contemplation when you say
there's no self look all these rocks
they're constantly changing electrons
and atoms thus nothing is real thus
there is no self this is just a hollow
convention conventional speech and so on
no that's that's not what it would have
said because you can say because
conventions are real as such yeah you
might not call itself but the thing is
that phenomena that you refer to
yourself it's there if it weren't there
you wouldn't be able to refer to it
whatsoever so dismissing the reality
does not remove your ownership of that
reality
which means ah so I should be concerned
with me appropriating reality not being
concerned about dismantling conventions
and proving the that nothing
exists CU that's that's like instead of
treating the illness in regard to the
body you just go and chop up the body
and say see the body can be chopped up
thus it's not real no it is real as a as
a collection of parts that can be
chopped up that's a reality and that was
never a problem
so there is that self there is that
sense of
self it's not that there is no self but
what you should do is remove the
ownership of that sense of self and then
it becomes
anata as in not
myself because it a practice of denial
and actually I don't want to say not
myself because then people might assume
ah someone else's self no anata is
self that you don't own and that cannot
be called self so it's not self so that
which was taken self still there but now
it's not taken is not
self but people are concerned with
denying that which is taken itself which
is an aspect of their experience one way
or the other but as the Buddha said the
five Aggregates are not the Assumption
and not the holding the view of the self
but there is no view of the self apart
from the five Aggregates so it's desire
and lust in regard to the five agregates
that the view of self is there but you
coming and saying there's no self the
five agates are impermanent there is no
self you're just dismissing it the
problem and without actually uh
understanding it because if you were to
if you were to truly understand it well
the only way to truly understand it is
to free yourself from that self to see
it as not self so any explanation that
you think you understood unless it's
freeing you from that sense of self
don't think you understood
it cuz people can put a lot of time and
effort in denial practice denial just
den den deny it for years and years many
of the meditation methods and techniques
are all based on that view of just
denial and seeing the moment to moment
movement that will kind of show you that
somehow things are not really real
cannot be yours but that that whole
practice goes completely against
being self transparent honest authentic
yeah saying this I do experience this
self I do experience this thing there is
mother there is there is Father there is
giv is offend there's no gender yeah
well okay people can deny anything
whatever they please um as the attitude
yeah it can be aim literally at anything
that's why the bud said the right the
worldly Right View is the view that
acknowledges the validity of of of
random phenomena a phenomena in your
experience no there is this there is
there is given there is Tak there is
mother there is Father there is The
Liberation there is the P allowing like
you don't need to see them and of course
you don't see them at that level but you
need to know
that there is a possibility of them
being being real as in there is a
possibility of being
free but if you keep denying everything
you will never accept that possibility
as a present phenomena and that's the
key accepting possibilities as a present
negative phenomena in your experience
yeah it's real the possibility is real I
don't know how to what extent but I
could find out if I apply
myself so you you don't want to deny
anything really you want to restrain
yourself from what you were told it's un
wholesome G of ver delusion that you can
see that it's un wholesome and then
within that you don't need to deny
further there will be like overshooting
the up you want to understand what's in
front of you that's what Budd said the
whole universe is contained within
this less than 6 foot long body and so
on he didn't say this body is not real
thus none of the universe is real
there's not there is no travel there is
no mother there's no father there's no
life cuz there were those views at the
time that he quite heavily criticized ah
nobody gets killed there's nothing it's
just elements just and actually modern
interpretation of Buddha anata it's
actually one of those wrong views back
in the day that the Buddha criticized
when they say everything is comprised of
constantly changing electrons and so
nothing is real or nothing nothing can
be mine there is no self and people
believe that whereby they said oh nobody
gets killed even if you go and cut
everybody on the left side of genes with
a sharp sword nobody gets killed all
that happens is the the the like the
sword runs through the elements
runs through the electrons and atoms you
can just call it whatever you want the
view is the same and the would say it's
completely wrong view because you're
blaming the five Aggregates for your
assumption for your sense of self
failing to see that it's desire and Las
in regard to the five Aggregates that
the sense of self is there but it's not
the five Aggregates so you killing the
five Aggregates does not free you from
the sense of self hence person who is
not freed from the sense of self when
the five agates dis disintegrate as in
when they die they're still there
they get reborn yeah it reminds me of
when someone's got a a problem and I
start you know complaining about trying
to talk it out and then H I don't know
the answer but anyway anyway
everything's impermanent so yeah anyway
it's it's okay so it's like this oh well
oh I've got this problem but I'll just
deny it now no unfortunately it's it's
it's it's it's prevalent as a view but
uh it's it's just rooted in in uh in
lazy self-reflection
like in in self-reflection that doesn't
go far
enough so then you just put a cap on it
by by by uh saying ah well it's all
impermanent anyway so I won't bother
with it I'll just you know watch my breath
it I'll just you know watch my breath
and be peaceful and live a simple life
you can live life
as as simply as you want as a vegetable
and still remain equally
ignorant and that's the problem it's not
how complex your life is of course you
want to simplify it because it can be
too much in like to start with to
practice but that's secondary it's just
creating the suitable condition for you
to understand what's right in front of
you but thinking that the goal of your
life is to simplify or to just to this
just do that without making the effort
to understand it and go through
that unpleasantness of unraveling the
the the Deep existential feelings of
fear and anxiety yeah there's no
practice without that for